Stella Bloch Hanau papers, 1890-1990
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Stella Hanau papers
1890-1990
Hanau, Stella, 1890-1972
MS 73
9 boxes (4 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Editor; Publicist; Birth control activist. Correspondence with family and associates in the birth control movement and the Works Progress Administration (1930s); birth control and WPA publications edited by Hanau; biographical information, memorabilia, photographs, and material for her book, The Provincetown: A Story of a Theatre (1931).
Stella Bloch was born in New York, New York, on July 24, 1890. Her father, Edward Bloch (1852-1933), and mother, Elizabeth Long (1861-1928), moved to New York from Alabama in 1882 after their cotton business sustained heavy losses. In New York, Edward Bloch went into the silk business, although family lore indicates that he was not a good businessman. Stella had three older brothers: Alexander (1881-1983), Samson Friedrich (1885-1936), and Eugene Godfrey (1888-1974). According to a biographical sketch by Stella's son, Richard Hanau, while Stella considered herself an agnostic, the family identified as Jewish though they did not attend temple or observe holidays.
After attending Wadleigh High School in Manhattan, Hanau earned a B.A. in English Literature from Barnard in 1911. While attending college she was secretary-treasurer for the Barnard chapter of the Collegiate Equal Suffrage League of New York, participated in the Intercollegiate Socialist Society, Deutscher Kreis, and the College Settlements Association. She also joined a variety of theatre groups and participated in productions. Just before college she met Hella Bernays, Sigmund Freud's niece, and the two became lifelong friends and collaborators.
In 1914 Stella married Leo Hanau (1884-1969), a New York City stockbroker. Originally from Mainz, Germany, Leo immigrated to New York in 1906, but remained a German citizen until the beginning of World War II. The Hanaus had a son, Richard, in 1918. They separated in 1921 and divorced in 1930.
During the 1920s Hanau acted as a press agent and publicity manager for several "experimental" theatres in New York City. These included the Greenwich Village Theatre and Neighborhood Playhouse, Playwrights Theater, and Provincetown Playhouse. Stella also co-authored, with Helen Deutsch, The Provincetown: A Story of the Theatre, in 1931 and managed Paul Robeson's first concert. Throughout her life she wrote and published playbills, press releases, and similar material related to theatre.
Hanau was also involved in the suffrage and birth control movements. She was editor of the Birth Control Review (1929-1933), editor and director of publications for the American Birth Control League (1933-1935), and educational director of the National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control (1935-1938). During her stint with the Birth Control Review, Hanau became friends with social service personnel and notable women in the birth control movement including Kitty Marion, Margaret Sanger, and early workers at Planned Parenthood. When Margaret Sanger left the American Birth Control League in 1935, Hanau left with her to work on publicity for Sanger in Washington.
Following her nearly fourteen years working for Margaret Sanger, Hanau went to work for the U.S. government. She was a staff editor for the Federal Writer's Project under the Works Progress Administration (1938-1942), an Information Specialist for the War Production Board (1942-1945), and Chief Copy Editor at the Department of Commerce (1945-49). She returned to New York City in 1949 where she worked as a free-lance editor. Among other projects, she collaborated with her lifelong friend Hella Bernays on the translation, indexing and editing of psychiatry books.
Stella Bloch Hanau died at age 81 on April 23, 1972, in Chelsea, New York.
The Stella Bloch Hanau Papers consist of 4 linear ft. and are related to her personal and professional life, dating from 1890 to 1990. Types of materials include correspondence, datebooks, employment records, news clippings, photographs, publications, publicity materials, theatrical playbills and programs, and memorabilia. The papers are arranged in three series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS
II. CORRESPONDENCE
III. ORGANIZATIONS
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
The bulk of the Papers date from 1910 to 1970 and consist in large part of correspondence. Approximately half of the correspondence is with family, especially Hanau's son Richard, his wife Laia, and their daughter Loren Michael. The rest of the correspondence is with Hanau's friends and associates in experimental theatre, the birth control movement, the Works Progress Administration (1930s), and in editing and publishing. Printed material includes birth control and WPA publications edited by Hanau as well as playbills from her theatre publicity days. Also included is biographical information, memorabilia, photographs, and material about Hanau's book, co-authored with Helen Deutsch, The Provincetown: A Story of the Theatre (1931).
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Stella Hanau's son, Richard Hanau, donated Stella Bloch Hanau's papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1971 to 1992.
Search Terms
American Birth Control League--History-; Planned Parenthood Federation of America--History; Birth control--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Birth Control Review--History; Federal Writers' Project--History; Provincetown Players--History; Women editors--United States--Biography--Sources; Experimental theater--United States--History--20th century; New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs--20th century; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966; Hanau, Stella, 1890-1972; Bernays, Hella; Macgowan, Kenneth, 1888-1963
Additional papers of Stella Bloch Hanau and Alexander and Blanche Bloch are housed at Barnard College and the University of Wyoming American Heritage Center.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS 1890-1990, 1 linear ft.
  This series includes biographical sketches, employment records, college memorabilia, news clippings, datebooks, legal documents, and photographs. Particularly revealing is an anecdotal sketch of Hanau written by her son, Richard.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1904-1974, 2.5 linear ft.
  This series consists of incoming and some outgoing correspondence. It is organized in two subseries: Family and Friends and associates. The Family subseries includes correspondence between Hanau and her brothers, father, and various extended family. The Friends and associates subseries contains both professional and personal correspondence. Notable correspondents include Kenneth MacGowan, Hella Bernays, Murray Bernays, and Roderick Seidenberg.
- SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS 1919-1969, 0.5 linear ft.
  This series consists of materials related to Hanau's work in the birth control movement, experimental theatre, and for the federal government. It is arranged alphabetically.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS
  - General, 1890-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Employment records and curriculum vitae, 1937-67, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barnard College
    - General, 1909-1913 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Equal Suffrage League, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family
    - General, 1917-62, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Edward Bloch [father], 1932-35, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Richard, Laia, and Loren Michael Hanau, 1928-70, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Marriage, 1914-30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Friends
    - M. Eleanor "Fitzi" Fitzgerald, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Kenneth MacGowan, 1919-57 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Marion Meisel, 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Hermann Muller, 1949-56 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous memorabilia, 1909-70, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Real estate
    - General, 1928-35 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 457 West 24th Street, New York, NY, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Patterson, New York (Box 1)
      - Williams property, 1925-63 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Tabb lot, 1942-54 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs
    - Stella Bloch Hanau and family, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Birth control-related, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Provincetown Players, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Diaries and planners
    - 1950-66 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    - 1967-72 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Family
    - Bloch, Alexander [brother], 1907-08, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Bloch, Blanche [sister-in-law], 1905-22, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Bloch, Edward and Elizabeth (Long) Bloch [parents], 1905-07 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Bloch, Eugene [brother], 1912-33, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Bloch, Marion, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Bloch, Samson [brother], 1907, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Hanau, Leo [husband], 1913-20, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Hanau, Leo (incoming, third party), 1914-19 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Hanau, Richard [son], 1918-36 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Hanau, Richard, Laia, and Loren Michael
      - 1941-55 (Box 4, Folder 10-20)
      - 1956-72, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-13)
    - Relatives in Germany, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - "Cousin Irma," 1904-08 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - "Cousin Sidney," 1904-09 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - "Cousin Walter," 1908-10 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 1907-33, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Friends and associates
    - Alsberg, Henry, 1929-31 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Barnett, Edith, 1910-23 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Bernays, Hella
      - Incoming, 1911-23 (Box 5, Folder 21-23)
      - Outgoing, 1912-17 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Bernays, Murray, 1916-22 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Borchard, Edwin, 1913-14 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Briggs, Janine, 1957-59 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Colby, Merle, 1950, 1962-64 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Colby, James and Vivienne, 1957-66 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Davenport, Mabel and Roderick, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - deLeon, Solon, 1912-13 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Deutsch, Helen, 1961-74 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Ellis, Havelock, 1931, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Gay, Katherine
      - Incoming, 1905-32 (Box 6, Folder 10-13)
      - Outgoing, 1907-22 (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
    - Goodman, Eddie, 1931-17 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Hamilton, G.V.1931 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Hastings, Mary E., 1913 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Herts, B. Russell, 1908-21 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Koch, Frank
      - Incoming, 1910-16 (Box 6, Folder 20-23)
      - Outgoing, 1910-12 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Lesher, Robert, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Levin, Ben, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Marks, Margot Strauss, 1908-22 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - MacGowan, Edna and Kenneth, 1914-57 (Box 7, Folder 6-8)
    - Meisel, Marion, 1921-22, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Muller, Hermann and Dorothy, 1930-67 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Naumberg, Carl, 1910-11 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Payne, Kenneth, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Price, Willard, 1912-13 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Randolph, Francis, 1908 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Solis, Caroline, 1916-20 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Schreiber, Lois Colby, 1963-64 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Schwitzer, Myrtle, 1912-16 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Seidenberg, Roderick, 1925-39 (Box 7, Folder 18-20)
    - Shepherd, Betty, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Smith, Olive, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Spier, Doris, 1903-21 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Stevens, Helen, 1963-69, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Symington, Varinka, 1968-69 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Von Wahl, Constance, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Weingart, Amelia and Lena, 1909-11 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Weingart, Sylvia, 1905-16 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Wengraf, Fritz and Gertrude, 1968-71, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Zucker, Marian, 1917-19, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "Agnes," 1908-21 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - "Bert B.S." 1909-13 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - "Clarissa" (Fairchild?) 1907-11 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - "Fritz," 1921 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - "Helen R." 1907 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - "Susan B.M." 1909-33 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous correspondents, A-Z (Box 8, Folder 9-10)
    - Unidentified, first name only, 1907-72, undated (Box 8, Folder 11-17)
- SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS
  - American Birth Control League, 1929-35 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control
    - 1934-35 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - 1936-37, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Provincetown Players and Greenwich Village Theatre
    - General, 1924-70, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Playbills, 1919-30 (Box 9, Folder 3-9)
    - Playbills project, 1924-65 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - The Provincetown: A Story of the Theatre
      - General, 1927-71, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Reprint, 1958-71 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - "Vote the New Moon" by Alfred Kreymborg: typescript, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - U.S. Civil Service Commission, 1937-48 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - U.S. Department of Commerce, 1945-49 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - War Production Board, 1942-45 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Washington Society for the Hard of Hearing, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Works Progress Administration (WPA), Writers' Project
    - General, 1940-42, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1938-68 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Publications, 1938-41 (Box 9, Folder 20-21)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Architects' drawings for addition to house, Patterson, NY, 1947 (Map-case flat file drawer 18)
  - SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS
    - Provincetown Players: program for "him" by e.e. cummings, 1928 (Map-case flat file drawer 18)
    - Office of War Information posters (2), undated (Map-case flat file drawer 18)